Guide to the Laurence MacDaniels papers, [ca. 1915]-1986.
Laurence MacDaniels papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Laurence MacDaniels papers, [ca. 1915]-1986.
21-25-815
L. H. (Laurence Howland), MacDaniels, 1888-1986.
39.9 cubic ft.
{**Comma Separated List Of Material Formats,End With Period**.}
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers include correspondence with other horticulturists, floriculturists, and pomologists mainly concerning the activities of the North American Lily Society, which he founded, the Northern Nut Growers Association, of which he was president, the American Society for Horticultural Science, and the American Horticultural Council; correspondence concerning the future of the Arnold Arboretum at Harvard University and the bread standards (1957-1958) set by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration; correspondence, reports, and translations (1959-1962) that document MacDaniels' mission as a consultant on nuts and small fruit for the Technical Assistance Administration of the Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia under programs sponsored by the U.S. International Cooperation Administration and the U.S. Agency for International Development; administrative correspondence of the Department of Floriculture and Ornamental Horticulture; correspondence with the American Association of University Professors in regard to the continued usefulness of retired professors; research notes and scientific photographs; manuscript, typescript and mimeographed lecture notes, course outlines, and examination questions; and printed matter relating to scientific organizations and other subjects; also, photoprints and negatives of Armenia (1919-1920), Florida and Maguay and Mexico (1921); Hawaii, Tahiti, Fiji, (1926), Samoa, Fiji, Tahiti (1927) and Lebanon (1944).
L.H. MacDaniels and his wife, Frances were involved with the American Committee for Relief in the Near East from 1919-1920 and his collection contains glass slides and negatives taken during the time of the Armenian genocide. Some of the images are copies of those taken by the Consul in Armenia at the time, Leslie Davis and are among the few images known to exist of the genocide. Many of the images are the same as those that appear in THE SLAUGHTERHOUSE PROVINCE by Leslie Davis, edited by Susan Blair. However, her book also contains images that are not included in this collection.
Also, legal documents, maps, an account book, and correspondence (1921, 1933-1934, 1936-1939) relating to the settlement of a family estate involving substantial interests in the Compañia Lechera "El Rosario" at Azcapotzalco, Mexico; the letters contain occasional comments on the farm labor situation in Mexico and government expropriation of farm land under the agrarian reform legislation of the period. Also, genealogical records of the Cochran and Allen families from 1882 to 1894; and a six-page manuscript by Cornell University Professor Damon Boynton entitled "The Hospice Idea," concerning his interview with L. H. MacDaniels in March 1982.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of floriculture and ornamental horticulture, Cornell University.
Professor of floriculture and ornamental horticulture, Cornell University.
Professor of floriculture and ornamental horticulture, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include correspondence with other horticulturists, floriculturists, and pomologists mainly concerning the activities of the North American Lily Society, which he founded, the Northern Nut Growers Association, of which he was president, the American Society for Horticultural Science, and the American Horticultural Council; correspondence concerning the future of the Arnold Arboretum at Harvard University and the bread standards (1957-1958) set by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration; correspondence, reports, and translations (1959-1962) that document MacDaniels' mission as a consultant on nuts and small fruit for the Technical Assistance Administration of the Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia under programs sponsored by the U.S. International Cooperation Administration and the U.S. Agency for International Development; administrative correspondence of the Department of Floriculture and Ornamental Horticulture; correspondence with the American Association of University Professors in regard to the continued usefulness of retired professors; research notes and scientific photographs; manuscript, typescript and mimeographed lecture notes, course outlines, and examination questions; and printed matter relating to scientific organizations and other subjects; also, photoprints and negatives of Armenia (1919-1920), Florida and Maguay and Mexico (1921); Hawaii, Tahiti, Fiji, (1926), Samoa, Fiji, Tahiti (1927) and Lebanon (1944).
L.H. MacDaniels and his wife, Frances were involved with the American Committee for Relief in the Near East from 1919-1920 and his collection contains glass slides and negatives taken during the time of the Armenian genocide. Some of the images are copies of those taken by the Consul in Armenia at the time, Leslie Davis and are among the few images known to exist of the genocide. Many of the images are the same as those that appear in THE SLAUGHTERHOUSE PROVINCE by Leslie Davis, edited by Susan Blair. However, her book also contains images that are not included in this collection.
Also, legal documents, maps, an account book, and correspondence (1921, 1933-1934, 1936-1939) relating to the settlement of a family estate involving substantial interests in the Compañia Lechera "El Rosario" at Azcapotzalco, Mexico; the letters contain occasional comments on the farm labor situation in Mexico and government expropriation of farm land under the agrarian reform legislation of the period. Also, genealogical records of the Cochran and Allen families from 1882 to 1894; and a six-page manuscript by Cornell University Professor Damon Boynton entitled "The Hospice Idea," concerning his interview with L. H. MacDaniels in March 1982.
SUBJECTS
Names:
MacDaniels, L. H. (Laurence Howland), (Laurence Howland), 1888-1986.; Boynton, Damon.; Boynton, Damon; American Committee for Relief in the Near East.; American Association of University Professors.; American Horticultural Council.; American Society for Horticultural Science.; Arnold Arboretum.; Compañia Lechera El Rosario.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Department of Floriculture and Ornamental Horticulture.; North American Lily Society.; Northern Nut Growers Association.; United States. Agency for International Development.; United States. Food and Drug Administration.; United States. International Cooperation Administration.; American Association of University Professors; American Horticultural Council; American Society for Horticultural Science; Arnold Arboretum; Irrigation Improvement Project (Egypt); New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Department of Floriculture and Ornamental Horticulture; North American Lily Society; Northern Nut Growers Association; United States. Food and Drug Administration; United States. International Cooperation Administration
Subjects:
Armenian massacres, 1915-1923; Agriculture -- Study and teaching.; Bread.; Floriculture.; Fruit -- Research.; Horticulture.; Medical care.; Terminal care facilities.; Hospices (Terminal care); Water -- Fluoridation.; Walnuts.; Bougainvillea -- Varieties.; College teachers.; Environmental protection -- Ithaca.; Floriculturists.; Horticulturists.; Pomologists.; Fruit.; Fruit-culture.; Agriculture -- Research; Agriculture -- Study and teaching; Bougainvillea -- Varieties; Bread; College teachers; Environmental protection; Floriculture; Floriculturists; Fruit; Fruit-culture; Fruit -- Research; Horticulture; Horticulturists; Hospices (Terminal care); Medical care; Political science; Terminal care facilities; Water -- Fluoridation
Places:
Azcapotzalco (Mexico City, Mexico); Mexico -- Research.; Mexico -- Politics and government.; Yugoslavia. -- Technical Assistance Administration.; Maguay; Mexico; Samoa; Tahiti; Lebanon; Philippines; Turkey; French Polynesia -- Tahiti (Island); Lebanon; Mexico; Mexico -- Azcapotzalco; New York (State) -- Ithaca; Philippines; Samoa; Turkey; Yugoslavia
Form and Genre Terms:
Genealogies.; Photographs.; Pictorial works
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- AAUP - Retirement, 1955-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Original first draft manuscript "How Can the University Make Better Use of Its Retired Professors?"; personal notes, correspondence with G. Streib, R.D. Anthony, W.P. Tufts; facts of retirement
- Outline of book on pruning, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes original first drafts of "The Pruning of Woody Plants"; class outlines and outlines of chapters.
- Sabbatic Leave 1949 general, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Correspondence regarding New Caledonia trip and tropical horticulture in South America, Costa Rica; travel arrangements and personal notes.
- Hawaii conservation and deer, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondence with Mr. Otton Degener of Waialua, Oahu; Mr. Herbert W. Levi, Department of Zoology, University of Wisconsin; C.G. Lennox, Board of Agriculture and Forestry, Honolulu; bulletins, newspapers clippings, maps.
- Sabbatic Leave - Cattala and Noumea, Luc, Chevalier, MacMillan, Barrau, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  New Caledonia collections - some personal some professional correspondence; receipts and cancelled checks.
- Bass-Becking, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Correspondence with L.G.M. Bass-Becking; South Pacific Commissions, lists of publications of Baas-Becking; Chronica-Botanica
- Sabbatic leave 1949 material since return, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Wood collectors, Swain Warner, Fairchild Tropical Gardens; correspondence regarding New Caledonia and South Pacific.
- Sabbatic Leave - Dr. J.T. Buchholz, New Caledonia, et cetera., 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Correspondence with Buchholz and Tippo regarding New Caledonia business; notice of Buchholz's death 1 July 1950.
- National Research Council - Pacific Science Board - Dr. H.J. Coolidge, Ryerson, Akers, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Correspondence with H.J. Coolidge, Ernestine Akers, Knowles Ryerson of Agricultural Experiment Station Davis, California; shipping invoices and various bills regarding New Caledonia.
- Sabbatic Leave - South Pacific Commission - Mac-Millan, Hunt; Institut Franaise d'Oceanie - Bugnicourt, Guillaumin, 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- David Fairchild, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Correspondence with Fairchild regarding the Pacific Collections.
- (Pomology) Course 243, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Examination questions
- L. H. MacDaniels - Course 243 - Lecture Notes and Outline, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes final examination with scoring notations.
- L.H. MacDaniels Course 243 - Notes - Laboratory Outlines, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  (Morphology and Anatomy of Fruit Plants)
- Course 11 Propogation - Lectures - L. H. MacDaniels, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Includes 1st draft of first lecture. (Course 115)
- Floriculture Department Course 11 Propogation, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Lab blanks, discussion of experiments, et cetera.
- L.H. MacDaniels - Propogation Outlines - Course 11, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Includes 1st lecture draft; notes and lab outlines
- Propogation - Course 11, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Propagation Course #11 Examinations, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Research - Dr. Haig Derman, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Correspondence
- G.L. Slate - NNGA, NALS, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Correspondence with G.L. Slate regarding horticultural matters, some personal
- 4-H Club Bulletins (1947), Miscellaneous Messages (1945), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Speeches - Personal, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Hand written notes and 1st drafts of speeches and reports
- L.H. MacDaniels - Leaflet Revision, 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Some bulletins (USDA, Cornell Extension...); correspondence with H.C. Campbell; 1st draft manuscripts of various articles
- Manuscripts Personal, 1940-1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Includes correspondence with D. Wyman
- L.H. MacDaniels - Revision, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Includes various articles; lecture outlines; manuscripts and revision for entry in Encyclopedia Britannica (1939)
- Pomology Text - Notes and Manuscripts, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Includes correspondence with McGraw-Hill
- Personal, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  1st draft of manuscript: "The Social Implications of the Scientific Method," with correspondence with L.S. Cottrell Jr.; manuscript: "Nursery Research at Cornell"
- Lily Article - Flower Grower, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Manuscript: "Experiences w/Eastern North American Lilies in the Garden." (1952)with correspondence with T.A. Weston; Manuscript: "The Kinds of Lilies"; manuscript: "Lilies of the Eastern United States"; manuscript: "Scouting for Lilium supurbum"
- Abstracts of Published Articles, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- The Compost Pile - Leaflet Revision, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Includes manuscripts of "The Compost Pile" with revisions and negatives; copy of: "The Truth about Organic Gardening"; manuscript: "Facts about Organic Gardening"; newspaper clippings; correspondence with Rural New Yorker (1952)
- "Lamb" Curly Grain Walnut - Manuscripts, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Notes, bulletins, 1st drafts of manuscript, correspondence with M.Y. Pillow; J.W. McKay; F. Wallick; J.F. Wilkinson; Forest Products Laboratory; W.C. Finley; F. Baker; Spencer Chase
- Revisions of articles - Botanical Society, etc., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Correspondence with R.E. Cleleand and revision
- Statler Club 1956-57 with brochures of 1950, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Correspondence regarding Statler Club business
- American Horticultural Council, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Correspondence with F. Howlett; P. Alampi; D. Wyman; H. Coolidge
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts Not Personal, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Orchid Collection at Cornell, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  List of orchid collection
- Botany One Syllabus, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Botany One Lecture Syllabus, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Botany One Laboratory Syllabus, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Garden Centers - Rochester, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  bulletins of various garden centers
- Facts for Home Gardeners, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  #1-9
- Facts for Florists, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 43)
- American Association of Nurserymen, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Articles I-VII
- New York Nursery Notes, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  various volumes
- General Horticultural Teaching, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Report on 1st courses in Horticulture at Land Grant Colleges
- Materials and Methods, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  Botany leaflet from Muenscher
- Pomology Miscellaneous, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Course outline
- Slate - Lecture Notes - Varieties Course, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Includes correspondence with G.L. Slate
- No Title, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Bulletins
- Envelope - Fertilizer Article, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Envelope - Photograph of the Office, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Envelope - Fertilizer Story, Date Unknown (Box 1, Folder 53)
- 4 prints of 1956 wall calendar, 1956 (Box 1)
- Small black box with medal, 1948-07-13 (Box 1)
  From the Massachusetts Horticultural Society awarded to LHM and G.L. Slate "for a miscellaneous collection of named lilies July 13, 1948
- General, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  General correspondence (including S.L. Emsweller, D. Wyman) from 1947 regarding departmental business.
- General Correspondence - Current, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes: correspondence with C.B. Beck of University of Glasgow regarding Earres' award of LL.D. - other - general Departmental Correspondence
- Lily Soils, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  General extension correspondence
- Lily Culture, 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  General correspondence, e.g. inquiries on lily culture
- Extension Correspondence - Current, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence - Special Persona, 1918-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes 2 letters: 1 - (1918) from O.F. Curtis; 1 - (1937) from (illegible signature - no envelope)
- General Correspondence 1955, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Includes: G.L. Slate (1955); notice of death of Ken Post. 1955; Phil Alampi
- General Correspondence 1954, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Includes: A.J.Heinicke (1955); D. Wyman (1954); G.L. Slate (1954); regarding department business
- Extension Correspondence - 1953, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  From December 1952 - December 1953
- Extension Correspondence - 1954, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  From January 1954 - January 1955
- General Correspondence - 1945, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Includes: J.R. Smith - 1945, H.B. Tuckey 1945
- General Correspondence - 1946, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- General Correspondence - 1948, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Includes: S.L. Emsweller (1948); G.S. Avery (1948); W.G. Brierley (1948); H.B. Tuckey (1948)
- General Correspondence - 1949, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- General Correspondence - 1950, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- General Correspondence - 1951, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- General Correspondence - 1952, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  From January 1952 - October 1952. Includes: D. Wyman ('52); S.L. Elmsweller ('52)
- General Correspondence - 1953, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Pi Alpha Xi, 1941-1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Newsletters, et cetera.
- Association of Scientists at Cornell University, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Constitution; newsletters
- Alpha Gamma Rho, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Membership roll; initiation certification LHM
- Gamma Alpha, 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Newsletters, treasury report
- International Association, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Correspondence with D.C. Kerr 1951 - regarding election of LHM as President
- Lazy Club, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Research Club of Cornell University, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Membership list (54-55); newsletter (51); membership list (50-51)
- American Society for the Advancement of Science, 1943-1952 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- American Institute of Crop Ecology, 1947-1952 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- American Plant Life Society, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- American Iris Society, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- American Rose Society, 1947-1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- American Delphinum Society, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Bergen Swamp Preservation Society, 1950-11-01 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Report
- Foundation for Economic Education, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- International Union of Biological Sciences, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- National Garden Conference, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- National Science Foundation, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- New York Academy of Sciences, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- International Horticultural Congress, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Horticultural Society of New York, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Pamphlets and correspondence
- National Research Council, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Phi Kappa Phi, 1940-1954 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Correspondence and initiation certificate (1940)
- Unitarian Society, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- A.H.C. (American Horticultural Council, Incorporated) L.R. Hubbard (Secretary of A.H.C.), 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Correspondence regarding AHC - fiscal concerns; membership; meeting minutes (10 March 1954); Secretary report to Board of Directors, Budget; Report of Treasury Office; Review of Flower Color Detector; list of officers, Executive Committee, and Board of Directors, Commission and Committee Membership. 1954-1955. Material not in folder: Proceedings of 9th Annual American Horticultural Congress and American Horticultural Council 27-30 Oct. 1954; brochure of American Horticultural Council; AHC News Dec.'55; correspondence with W.J. Jones, manager of Convention Department Chamber of Commerce, Houston, TX - regarding facilities for meeting 28 Mar. 1956
- Phil Alampi, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Correspondence with LHM regarding American Horticultural Council, including exchange with Donald Wyman. December 1955-April 1956
- Donald Wyman, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Correspondence with LHM - regarding AHC - January-February 1956
- American Horticultural Council Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Brochures for AHC; proceedings of 10th Annual meeting 26-29 Oct. 1955 - committee reports 9 May 1956
- American Horticultural Council News, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  1 copy AHC News, March 1956
- American Horticultural Council Judging Schedule and Returned Questionnaires, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Returned completed questionnaires from various Horticulture Societies in U.S. Regarding: judging validity and practices.
- American Horticultural Council 1955 Meeting, Washington DC, Judging Committee Report, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Compilation of answers to a judging questionaire; correspondence regarding judging schedule and program and training programs, with various individuals, organizations, universities, experiment stations etc.; copy of "Planning and Staging Flower shows" by Victor H. Ries; copy of "Judge Training Program for Horticulturists"by LHM 12 September 1955. All correspondence September-October 1955
- American Horticultural Council Judging Schedule - Letters and Catalogues, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  AHC Judging Schedule - Letters and Catalogues 1954 correspondence - regarding judging schedules and training programs. Includes a report on "Present Day Judging Standards - Cattleyas" by Robert M. Scully, Miami, FL; "Handbook on Judging and Exhibition" from American Orchid Society, 1949; "Flower Show schedules" by Victor H. Ries; "Rule Book for Exhibitors and Judges at the Exhibitions of the Massachusetts Horticultural Society" 5th Edition, 1947; Judging Schedule for Shows from American Fuchsia Society; Information Handbook for Exhibition Judges and Rules of American Iris Society.
- L.H. MacDaniels - AHC Congress, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Minutes of the meting in New York City 2 Feb 1954; Treasurer's Report 12 May 1954 for 1 April-1 May 1954; Secretary Report 12 May 1954; Minutes of AHC meeting in New York City 12 May 1954; minutes of meeting in New York City 14 April 1954; minutes of meeting in NYC 11 Jan. 1954; correspondence regarding meetings; agenda of Executive Committee Meeting 14 Sept/ 1954; Minutes of meeting in NYC 6 Oct 1954
- American Horticultural Council Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Correspondence with members regarding meetings, business at hand, etc.; minutes to meeting in Boston, MA 20 Oct. 1954; Tentative Program for meeting in Boston, MA 26-29 Oct. 1955; minutes of meeting Boston, MA 30 Oct. 1954; minutes for meeting in Boston, MA 27 Oct. 1954; minutes for meeting in Boston, MA 30 Oct. 1954
- American Horticultural Council Meeting Washington 1955 October Exhibit, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Form correspondence to members; preliminary program brochure; AHC News July 1955,Oct. 1955, May 1955; list of active members - 20 Oct. 1955; list of registrants 10th Annual Horticultural Congress 26-29 Oct. 1955; correspondence between LHM and various members Sept-Oct. 1955
- American Horticultural Congress - Carl F. Wedell, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Correspondence with C.F. Wedell from November 1953-November 1955 - regarding general AHC business
- L.H. MacDaniels - American Horticultural Council - Judges, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Notes on judging and school; correspondence; minutes to meeting in NYC 14 Apr. '54; minutes to meeting in NYC (Board of Directors) 10 March '54; copies of judging questionnaire
- AHC Editorial Comittee - Gillespie, Carleton, Kelley, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Correspondence between Freeman Howland and M. Carleton regarding publications Nov. 1952